<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A funeral sermon on the death of Mrs. Mary Paice, late wife of Mr. Joseph Paice, merchant of Clapham, who died April 8th, 1700 by Edmund Batson.</title>
            <author>Batson, Edmund.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26823</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1141</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4308</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13079149</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13079149</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97222</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26823)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97222)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 407:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A funeral sermon on the death of Mrs. Mary Paice, late wife of Mr. Joseph Paice, merchant of Clapham, who died April 8th, 1700 by Edmund Batson.</title>
                  <author>Batson, Edmund.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 61 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuel Bridge ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Paice, Mary, d. 1700.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97222:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97222:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Funeral Sermon ON THE DEATH OF Mrs. <hi>Mary Paice,</hi> Late Wife of Mr. <hi>Joſeph Paice</hi> Merchant OF CLAPHAM.</p>
            <p>Who Died <hi>April</hi> 8th. 1700.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Edmund Batſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Samuel Bridge</hi> in <hi>Auſtin-Fryers,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="modern_bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:97222:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <head>Academiae Tantabrigiensis Liber.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:97222:2"/>
            <head>To His much Reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Friend Mr. <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph Paice</hi> Merchant.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THO' no Man can <hi>put aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> whom God hath <hi>joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together;</hi> yet if <hi>He</hi> who makes the <hi>Union</hi> will make a <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> Who durſt ſay, <hi>what doeſt thou?</hi> The abſolute Soveraignty of God, and his irreſiſtable Power conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, hath repreſſed the Exorbitant Paſſions of <hi>Heathens</hi> under Temporal Evils: Though the Goſpel aſſiſts us with divers more ſpecial and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Arguments, yet we often come ſhort of their Sedate Temper and Self-Government.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97222:3"/>
            <p>Your Affliction muſt be confeſſed Great, in the loſs you ſuſtain: And though the Advances of Death were from Time to Time apprehended, yet its Arreſt was ſudden; and this gives no ſmall Accent to the Calamity. But the Subject of the enſuing Diſcourſe is capable of affording Relief, Great and Suitable.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of a Glorious Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is propounded by the Apoſtle, as a particular Lenitive to moderate Sorrow upon the Departure of our deareſt Friends, who die in the Lord, <hi>1 Theſſ. 4.13, 14.</hi> Its Efficacy and our Advantage by that Article depends upon our believing it: <hi>If ye believe that Chriſt died and roſe again, even ſo them alſo which ſleep in Jeſus will God bring with him.</hi> There is great Reaſon to believe your departed Relative among the number that ſleep in Jeſus, ſo that your Peace and Comfort will be according to the Degree of your Faith in his Death and Reſurrection.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97222:3"/>
            <p>I confeſs, it owing to your Self, that I inſiſted on this Subject, or rather a Particular Interpoſure of Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, which without praevious Thoughts or Inſpection fixed both your Eye and Mind together on this Text. I cannot omit to mention it as a thing which deſerves a thankful Remark, that in ſo dark and ſad a Seaſon, you ſhould be led to ſo bright and Joyful an Argument. What could have been ſuggeſted more Great and Support<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing!</p>
            <p>The direct Influence this Truth hath upon the Life of Man in General ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it uſeful to all; <hi>As there is no Man liveth, and ſhall not ſee Death,</hi> Pſalm <hi>89.48.</hi> So no Man that dieth, and ſhall not be raiſed: And ſince the kind of our Reſurrection will be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to our Manner of Living and Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, this neceſſarily claims our beſt Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection and Diligence. Our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural State is that of Apoſtates or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volters from God: The Great Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb facs="tcp:97222:4"/>of ſuch Creatures is Converſion or Re-union with God through Chriſt. When we thus return and enter our Selves into the number of His Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Renewed ones, we becomes enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled to Redeeming Grace in all its Parts. And who is there that would not be redeemed? That would not (how ſlight ſoever his Preſent Thoughts are) when it comes to the utmoſt Point, give the whole World were it his, to be ſaved from Wrath and Hell? That would not rather with the aſſured Chriſtian commit his departing Spirit into the Hands of God, and his Fleſh to a hopeful Reſt in the Grave, than to fall under the Seizure of the Devil, and the Arreſt of Death together? The great Danger is leaſt Men deceive themſelves by ſeparating between the Effects and Benefits of Renewing and Redeeming Grace, and therefore I have taken ſome Care to Guard againſt this, as the limits of the Time and Diſcourſe would allow. I know Men are ſecretly diſſatisfied
<pb facs="tcp:97222:4"/>with the Terms of God; they would be Redeemed, but not ſubject to the Redeemer; they would live to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and when they can live no longer, would Die in the Lord: But this is ſo Groſs, they dare not utter it; and ſo full of Guilt, as that it will effectually conſign them to an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſible State of Diſſatisfaction and Torment for ever.</p>
            <p>I am Glad, that while I comply with your Requeſt in the Publication of this, I can alſo teſtifie the great Reſpect I bore to the Perſon whoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe occaſioned it, and contribute in this way to the Embalming Her Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Name. I ſhall not fail to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect my beſt Deſires to God, that He (who alone can) would fill up every Relation vacated by <hi>Her</hi> removal, by more plentiful Communications of Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; that <hi>Her</hi> Humble and Pious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample may live in <hi>your</hi> Memory; that <hi>Her</hi> hopeful <hi>Deſcendants</hi> may tread in <hi>Her</hi> ſteps; that you may all
<pb facs="tcp:97222:5"/>attain to the ſame full Aſſurance of Hope; that God <hi>will be your God and Guide unto Death,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Redeem You from the Power of the Grave, and receive You, that you may all (together with Her) be for ever with the Lord: In whom I am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Affectionate Servant, <hi>Edmund Batſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:97222:5"/>
            <head>A Funeral Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalm 49.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But God will redeem my Soul from the power of the Grave; for he ſhall receive me. Selah.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is generally known on <hi>whoſe and what account</hi> we are now to divert from our uſual Courſe and Subject: If the Determination of Events had been in our Judgments and Wills, our preſent aſſembling had been rather to have adored and praiſed Divine Goodneſs for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of our <hi>Deceaſed Siſter</hi> than
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97222:6"/>as now mournfully to ſolemnize <hi>Her</hi> Funeral, But our <hi>Exit</hi> no more depends on our Judgments or Wills than our Entrance into this World; which is not at all, but the Keys of Life and Death are in the Hands of One, who worketh all things ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Counſel of his own Will, and whoſe Judgment and will is as much more kind and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial to us, as more true and Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial than ours can be: And tho we ſhould ſuppoſe (as we are too apt to do) our Underſtandings and Deſires altogether free from Irregularity and Miſtake. Yet our Impotency keeps us unfit for ſuch a Province as deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining events; eſpecially the Grand and comprehenſive events of <hi>Life</hi> and Death, to which Omnipotency is equally neceſſary, with Unerring Wiſdom: No leſs a power can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue Life than that which can create or give it: By all our Thoughts and Labour, and Subſtance, we can no more add a Year, or a Day, to our,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97222:6"/>Time, than a Cubit to our Stature, the bounds of both being immutably fixed: Who can ſtop the Conqueſts of Death? Notwithſtanding the ſummoned Advice of Man, the Uſe of all things which Wiſdom or Skill may direct, and Wealth procure, and ſanctified too by inceſſant Supplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the ſupreme Being, Death is ſtill Victorious: It irreſiſtable intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces it ſelf whether we are willing or unwilling; ready and prepared or not: Such as converſed with us, took ſweet Counſel together with us in the Houſe of God, delighted themſelves with us, and gave us de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, become Death's Captives be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Eyes, are bound in its Bonds: And we can no more ſave our ſelves than reſcue or redeem them: And this indeed would be a moſt <hi>Mournful Caſe,</hi> if either.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>There was no one that could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem them;</hi> if there was no power Superior to their own that could effectually break the Gates of Death,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97222:7"/>and loſe them from its Bonds: if there could be none found that might be, <hi>par negotio,</hi> competent for ſuch a work: Or if,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>They were ſuch as were not to be redeemed;</hi> but to be left under the power of Death: ſo that their dying out of this World ſhould be a certain introduction of the ſecond Death which is Eternal, if they were found without thoſe qualifications, that might Rank them among that number to whom the Almighty Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer hath appropriated and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined his Care and Power.</p>
            <p>In either of theſe caſes Chriſtians cannot without inexpreſſible Grief behold the Conqueſt Death makes over Apoſtate Creatures, and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the <hi>Exit</hi> of a Sinner, becauſe it is his Entrance into a place of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from whence there is no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
            <p>In either of theſe Caſes <hi>Relatives</hi> may with ſome colour of Reaſon abandon themſelves to ſorrow and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97222:7"/>Mourn as thoſe without hope, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they really are ſuch.</p>
            <p>But this is not the caſe here, Death and the Grave in our preſent View is not ſo mournful a Spectacle: Their aſpect, (which is always various according to the State of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon related to) is not ſo Frightful and Horrid: Inexorable Death, its true, hath ſuddenly ſnatched away one from us, and the Grave hath ſwallowed Her up. But Help is laid on one that is mighty to ſave. There is one that <hi>hath deſtroy'd him, that hath the power of Death, that is the Devil:</hi> Heb. 2.14. And therefore can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem a ſoul from the power of the Grave and ſwallow up Death and the Grave in Victory. As he hath abſolute Power over this Viſible World of ours and doth meaſure out the time which each of its Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants is to ſpend here. So Death and the Grave are alſo within the limits of his Dominion: and an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of emitting thence is conjunct
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97222:8"/>with his Authority and Power of commanding our Entrance into it: Neither is it to be queſtioned, but that Perſon on whom Death hath now laid its hand and tranſmitted to the Grave, is intereſted in and under the cuſtody of that Benign Power which will in a ſeaſonable time bring her up from thence.</p>
            <p>The ſupporting Vertue of this and ſuch like Truths to the <hi>Deceaſed</hi> under her Chronical Diſtempers, and the Conſolatory uſe of it, to her <hi>Surviving Conſort</hi> hath given him juſt Reaſons for the Recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Text to be ſpoken to on this occaſion. <hi>But God will redeem my Soul from the Power of the Grave; for he ſhall receive me. Selah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Adverſative Particle, <hi>But,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers us to ſomething that was ſpoken before: The Doctrine of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection is inſinuated as a moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual remedy againſt inordinate fears and dejection of mind in an evil time: This hath an advantage
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97222:8"/>above other remedies becauſe it ſuits with the natural Diſpoſition of Mankind to draw relief under trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from a pre-apprehended Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: Thoſe who erroneouſly built their hopes of a Reſurrection upon their Wealth, and the multitude of their Riches, made it to ſerve for this purpoſe, but the unſervicableneſs of their Wealth and Wiſdom and the vanity of their Truſt thereon is detected by their daily ſubjection to Death, who not only <hi>cuts them down,</hi> as at <hi>verſe</hi> 7.8, 9, 10. but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards <hi>feeds on them:</hi> v. 14. And therefore tho the Doctrine be true and of ſoveraign and infallible uſe in ſuch caſes, yet becauſe the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of their Hopes is falſe they can have no ſafe retreat hither from their forementioned guilty Fears: But I build my Hope upon a truer bottom; tho their fears in an evil Day or Hour of Death may reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably remain, yet I have no reaſon to fear, for it is <hi>God, one that can
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97222:9"/>and one that will redeem my ſoul from the power of the Grave, and receive me, Selah.</hi> This is the plain connexion of the words with the precedent part of the <hi>Pſalm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall enquire into the true Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of both Phraſes, and then look upon them in their Mutual reſpect, and the light they caſt upon each other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But God will deliver my ſoul from the power of the Grave:</hi> The word <hi>Soul</hi> muſt be taken in an accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date Senſe, and, without enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the various Expoſitions, it ſeems moſt properly to ſignifie the Humane Life, not the Soul or Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſingly, but the Union between both, becauſe this is that, that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the Interciſion by Death: And this Metonymical Conſtruction is ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by many Places of Scripture, where the Circumſtances of the Text do at firſt view determine this to be the true and only Senſe of the Word: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.12. <hi>He hath poured out his Soul
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97222:9"/>unto Death,</hi> compared with <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.28. <hi>And to give his Life a Ranſom for many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>From the Power of the Grave:</hi> The <hi>Original</hi> Word is comprehenſive of the whole unſeen World, both in its Upper and Lower, in its Happy and Miſerable Regions. The known Controverſie in which this Word is concerned, hath occaſioned a fuller ſearch into its Primitive and Ancient Signification. And though it be of that Latitude, yet its Senſe is pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar according to the Circumſtances of the Place wherein it is uſed: And here, I conceive, it is moſt proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood of the State and Place of the Dead, ſo that the import of the Expreſſion, <hi>God will redeem my Soul from the Power of the Grave;</hi> is, That he will not leave me in that State wherein Death lodges me: Death will ſeparate my Soul and Body, and turn my Body to Duſt, but God will not ſuffer it to keep me always in that State: He
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97222:10"/>will not ſuffer it to Exerciſe a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Dominion over me: Tho' I am captivated by it, yet He who is ſtronger than Death will break its Bars, and give me a ſeaſonable. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe: The Word <hi>Redeem</hi> ſeems to govern and direct us in Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole Phraſe, and leads us ſo to conceive of the Power of the Grave, and our being in or under it, as that with Reference to it, the Word Redemption might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly applicable and uſed. And this Conſtruction is confirmed by that Parallel Text, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 13.14. where the Captivity of the <hi>Jews</hi> is called a Death, a being under the Power of the Grave: But ſaith God, <hi>I will ranſom them from the Power of the Grave, I will redeem from Death, O Death I will be thy Plague, O Grave I will be thy Deſtruction:</hi> But more fully by that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 16.9, 10. which though ſpoken by <hi>David</hi> concerning our Lord Chriſt, as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> determines,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97222:10"/>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 2.25, 26, 27. Yet may truly and properly be ſpoken of every ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chriſtian that is his Member: <hi>My Fleſh ſhall reſt in Hope, for thou wilt not leave my Soul in Hell, nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thine Holy one to ſee Corruption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For He ſhall receive me:</hi> i. e. He ſhall take me entirely to himſelf: The Form of our Covenant between us, is, that I ſhould give up both Body and Soul to him, and that he ſhould receive both, that where he is, I, in my whole Perſon, may be. He hath received me into his Grace and Favour: He hath accepted me in the Beloved; He hath adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me into his Family, that I am no more under the Dominion of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, as one of his Houſhold or Slaves: And this is a Pledge and Earneſt, that he will receive me to himſelf, into the Manſions of his Glory; where I ſhall no more fear the Arreſt of Death, or be moleſted with any other natural Evils.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:97222:11"/>
            <p>Now having ſeen the Senſe of the Words; there is ſomething materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to be obſerved; if we look on them in their <hi>Mutual</hi> Aſpect, and Relation to each other. And</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>latter</hi> Part of the Words doth direct and confine our Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of the <hi>former:</hi> There is a Reſurrection both of the Juſt and Unjuſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.15. Theſe are ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified by their different Ends: One is a Reſurrection unto <hi>Life,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unto <hi>Damnation,</hi> John 5.9. And it is determined, which Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection muſt be here meant, by that which is added, <hi>For He ſhall receive me:</hi> All muſt be rais'd, and though it is by the ſame Almighty Power, yet not to the ſame ultimate Purpoſe and End: Some are rais'd, that they may be ſent into the moſt remote and reimpaſſible Diſtance from God: Others, that they may be taken into the neareſt Union with him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a <hi>Mutual Security</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred from the Expreſſions on each
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97222:11"/>other. <hi>But God will redeem my Soul from the Power of the Grave, for he ſhall receive me:</hi> He muſt firſt redeem me from out of the Hands of Death, before he can receive me: My final Bleſſedneſs conſiſts in my Reception with him: This Bleſſedneſs muſt reach to the Body (which is an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Part of the Man) as well as the Soul, otherwiſe it is not Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat and Perfect: And 'tis his Word, whereon he hath cauſed me to Hope, that <hi>where he is, his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſhall alſo be,</hi> John 12.26. This makes it neceſſary that the Body be raiſed: Good Actions, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is a part of Divine Service, or belongs to us to do as his Servants, though deſigned by the Counſel and Reſolution of the Spirit, yet are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the Miniſtry of the Fleſh: And the Body is the Conſort of the Soul in all its Obedience and Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: They muſt be both offered as one <hi>living ſacrifice to God, Rom.</hi> 12.1. They muſt both concur to render us
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97222:12"/>his Servants; therefore their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is neceſſary, that his Servants may be where he is.</p>
            <p>And becauſe it is a God, one who is infinitely powerful and faithful, that is, to make me thus finally and perfectly Bleſſed, I have no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to doubt, <hi>But he will redeem my Soul from the Power of the Grave:</hi> His rewarding Goodneſs as well as his revenging Juſtice muſt be made manifeſt: And how can that be, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Body be raiſed, that the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Perſon may be capable of a juſt Recompence: If I am one of thoſe whom he will receive, it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that I ſhould be held under the Power of Death, or remain its Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive any longer, than for ſuch a Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as the Method and Order of his working makes needful.</p>
            <p>And there is an equal Neceſſity inferred alſo on the other ſide: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>He will redeem my Soul from the Power of the Grave,</hi> therefore <hi>He ſhall receive me</hi> to himſelf: There
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97222:12"/>is a <hi>Mutual Inſurance,</hi> becauſe it is equally impoſſible for a Believer to be redeemed from the Power of the Grave, and not be finally and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly Bleſſed, as to be perfectly Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed without being firſt redeemed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Mutual Relation between the Words, doth intimate a Manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of <hi>my belonging</hi> unto God: Reſurrection alone ſimply conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, doth not prove me to be his; but when he ſhall both raiſe me and receive me, it is thereby manifeſtly determined whoſe I am: Here it is ſtill liable to Queſtion, both as to my ſelf and others, To whom I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, and though I find this weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Queſtion ſometimes comſortably reſolved, yet at other times I cannot diſcern, or take the Comfort of, any ſuch Anſwer: But then it will be finally decided. Redemption from the Grave, is a demonſtrative Argument of his Intereſt in us, to which we cannot but Aſſent: As the <hi>Jews</hi> profeſſed a readineſs to believe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97222:13"/>that Chriſt belonged to God, and was his Son, if as a Father he would deliver him from the power of Death on the Croſs, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.43. The Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our Lords Relation to the Father was much eclipſed by his poor Life, and ignominious Death: And though his darkeſt Nights were enlightened with ſome diſcoveries of his Deity, yet they were vaniſhing and tranſient: But in his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he was declared to be the Son of God with Power, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4. And the Father publickly owned him in the Face of a contradicting World: The glorious Reſurrection of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers will be an illuſtrious and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing Evidence, that God is their God, and that they are his People.</p>
            <p>The Doctine or general Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the words is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>True believers tho they die, yet ſhall not perpetually remain in a ſtate of Death, but be raiſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived up into Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:97222:13"/>
            <p>That they die, as well as others, tho they are delivered from the Sting of Death, is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for divers reaſons<note n="*" place="margin">Bates of Death. cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note>, namely, for the more Eminent Exerciſe of their Grace, and Illuſtration of the Divine Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; for the preſerving a due and juſt difference between the Militant and Triumphant State of the Church: And that the ſinful frailties which cleave to them here may be aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and they prepared for the Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial life, of which the Natural Body is uncapable.</p>
            <p>And 'tis likewiſe neceſſary that they remain under the power of Death for a time: that the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Order of Providence might be preſerved;<note n="†" place="margin">Bates: ut ſupra.</note> and that the Glory of our Redeemer at his <hi>ſecond appearance</hi> might be greatned, together with their own Glory, by their ſimulraneous Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and Glorification, and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Entry with him into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97222:14"/>But it is not of this that we are to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>All are equally ſubject to the ſtroke of Death, but all are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain redeem'd from its power. Death and the Grave is not univerſally Overcome as to all: It ſtill remains a Conquerer over Multitudes, and will be finally victorious over them. But tho Death worketh in Believers and ſurronds them on every ſide, and at laſt gains a temporal conqueſt over their bodily Life: Yet hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that <hi>Vanquiſhed Life</hi> ſhall revive; and that more <hi>Noble Life</hi> which is <hi>hid with Chriſt in God,</hi> ſhall be conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate and made perfect. In this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent State Chriſtians may vanquiſh the fears of Death: But 'tis at their Reſurrection when their corruption ſhall have put on Incorruption, and their mortals ſhall have put on Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, that the ſaying ſhall be brought to paſs which is written: <hi>Death is ſwallowed up in Victory: O Death where is thy Sting? O Grave
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97222:14"/>where is thy Victory? Thanks be to God who giveth us Victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> 1 Cor. 15.54, 55, 56, 57. I ſhall briefly State the Grounds of the bleſſed Reſurrection of true Believers, and ſhew you its <hi>neceſſity,</hi> and then make ſome <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication</hi> of this Point.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Enſuring Grounds</hi> of a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers Reſurrection are principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>two.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Reſurrection of Chriſt: 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Knowing that he who raiſed up Jeſus from the dead will alſo raiſe us up by Jeſus.</hi> 1 Cor. 6.14. 1 Theſſ. 4.14. <hi>for if we believe that Jeſus died and roſe again, even ſo them alſo which ſleep in Jeſus will God bring with him.</hi> Chriſt roſe not as a Private, but as a Publick common Perſon. Our Nature was raiſed in his Perſon, and therefore in our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture all true Believers. <hi>He roſe as the Firſt Fruits of them that ſleep,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.20. And upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count our Reſurrection is ſecured;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97222:15"/>and not our Reſurrection meerly, but in all its happy Modifications and Iſſues; as the Firſt Fruits of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to God, did not only aſſure but ſanctifie the whole following Harveſt. And this ſecurity, tho of ſomething future, is ſo ſtrong that that the Apoſtle illuſtrates it by an oppoſite Inſtance wherein the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is actually and moſt lamentably felt: as at 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.21, 22. <hi>for as by Man came Death ſo by Man comes the Reſurrection from the Dead: As in Adam we all die: ſo in Chriſt ſhall we be made alive; but every man in his order, Chriſt the Firſt Fruits, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards them that are Chriſts at his coming:</hi> ſo that as our Death and the Death of all that ſhall come into Being, is ſecured by <hi>Adam's:</hi> ſo with an equal but more joiful cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty; the Reſurrection of Believers is ſecured by Chriſt; wherefore <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he lives they ſhall live alſo.</hi> John 14.19.</p>
            <p>This inferring a believers Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97222:15"/>from Chriſt is grounded on three reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) He is the <hi>Meritorious Cauſe</hi> of our Reſurrection. The Prayer of the Prophet, (as it engaged the Divine power) raiſed the <hi>Shunamites</hi> Child, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.33, 34. the dead Souldier revived at the touch of the Prophet's Bones, <hi>chap.</hi> 13.21. How much more ſhall the will of Chriſt and the power of his Death raiſe us.<note n="*" place="margin">Baxter<hi>'s Sts.</hi> Reſt. p. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi> Sect. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> He was our Surety when under the arreſt of Death, and making full ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Juſtice of God, merited not only our Impunity, but our Advancement: Now having fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the work of our Redmption by his ſufferings and Death, his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection is but the juſt conſequent of his Paſſion and Diſcharge or Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittance: upon this our Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is grounded, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>ult.</hi> Now the price being paid, and the Acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance received, there is no Barr a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>our</hi> happy Reſurrection any
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97222:16"/>more than againſt <hi>his,</hi> becauſe the Price was paid in our ſtead; and the Acquittance received is for the uſe of the principal Debter whoever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives it.</p>
            <p>Furthermore the Redemption of Chriſt extended to the Body as well as to the Soul; otherwiſe he had been but an incompleat Saviour, therefore Chriſtians who have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced the vertue of his redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grace, are ſaid to wait for the final act of his Redeeming Power in the <hi>Redemption of their Bodies.</hi> Rom. 8.23.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Athanas. de Inearnat. verbi.</note>Whether there ſhould have been no Reſurrection of the Body at all if Chriſt had not died, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he died ſo far for all both juſt and unjuſt to raiſe them, as ſome think. Or whether there ſhould have been a Reſurrection of the Body if Chriſt had not died, and Man ſhould have ſtill ſuffered both Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and Eternal Death, in <hi>toto
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97222:16"/>ſuppoſito,</hi> in his whole Perſon; as others think:<note n="†" place="margin">Cocceus de faedr. Cap. <hi>2.</hi> Sect. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly in the preſent or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Reſurrection of Believers muſt be aſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Merits of the Croſs, and looked upon as the fruit of Chriſts Death: ſo that it remains as ſure as the vertue and efficacy of his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) He is the <hi>effective Principal</hi> or cauſe of our Reſurrection: <hi>All pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is given him in Heaven and in Earth,</hi> He is the ſupport of our Bodily Life and the Author of that Spiritual Life we live as Believers, and by him all things are upheld and do conſiſt: therefore tis requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite that all things ſhould be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe beholden to him for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. It muſt be a Mediating Power; the power of a Mediator to preſerve things in being where their being is forfeited, and Annihilati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on deſerved; and likewiſe to heal the diſorders Sin hath introduced
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97222:17"/>among all kind of Beings that relate to the Uſe and Comfort of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate Man. And as he is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this Reſtitution among the Creatures, ſo likewiſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Man which will be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied therewith. By his <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Power</hi> and <hi>Agency</hi> wicked Men ſhall be raiſed: He is Lord of the whole unſeen State, who as he can commit, ſo can bring forth, having the Key of Death as well as of Life: He will exert his Power to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact the ſcattered parts of their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and as a <hi>Judge Authoritively</hi> Summon them to appear before him. But Believers are raiſed, tho not by an <hi>Inferiour,</hi> yet by a more <hi>benign</hi> and advantageous power: His own Reſurrection put him in the Poſſeſſion of that Power which do effectually ſecure ours, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.9. <hi>For to this end Chriſt both died and roſe, and Revived that he might be Lord both of the Dead and Living.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Chriſts Reſurrection is the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97222:17"/>
               <hi>Example</hi> or <hi>Pattern</hi> of a Believers: becauſe he aroſe, therefore they ſhall riſe and ſhall ſo ariſe as he did; and be reſtored to Life according to his Pattern: <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Our vile Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſhall be changed into the likeneſs of his moſt Glorious Body:</hi> His Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was raiſed the ſame, ſo ſhall ours, and yet his Body was improved by the Reſurrection, ſo ſhall ours too, and ſo much the more improved than his, as they need it more; whereupon as to our Bodily State we ſhall become <hi>like the Angels that are in Heaven,</hi> Mat. 22.30. As we ſhall be purged from all our preſent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, ſo we ſhall no longer need the means of bodily Suſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: for the <hi>Children of God which are the Children of the Reſurrection, are equal unto the Angels, and can die no more</hi> Luke 20.36. Our Lord was raiſed that he might aſcend and be glorified; ſo ſhall we, God will redeem our Souls from the Power of the Grave that he might <hi>receive us to himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:97222:18"/>
            <p>The <hi>Second Ground</hi> is,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Inhabitation of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: And this is a more immediate or proximate Foundation of this bleſſed Priviledge. Reſurrection ſimply conſidered, hath its depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance only on the Will and Power of God: but it is of a Glorious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection that we here ſpeak. The meer Reſurrection of the Body is abſolute, but a Reſurrection unto Glory is conditional, and therefore appropriate to ſome only; and the Author of this Glorious Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath determined to whom it ſhall be vouchſafed. He himſelf hath confined it to ſuch as have a work of Grace effectually wrought by the Spirit of Chriſt dwelling in them. Now the Inhabitation of the Spirit in Believers will more clearly appear as the <hi>Ground</hi> of their Reſurrection, by conſidering theſe two things</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) The Spirit of Holineſs is the <hi>vital bond of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion between Chriſt and Believers;</hi> by vertue of which uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97222:18"/>his Reſurrection doth aſſure theirs. Chriſt and Believers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute but one Myſtical Body; it is the Spirit of Holineſs which thus unites them, of which they both muſt neceſſarily tho not equally Partake. He is the Head, they are the Members, and therefore muſt have Communion with him in his Reſurrection and Life. Whatſoever <hi>Glorious</hi> or <hi>Inglorious Change</hi> the Head ſuffers, the Members muſt feel ſomething of the ſame in a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionate Degree: And this is ſo In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible that the Apoſtle argues not only from the Negation of Chriſts Reſurrection to the Negation of ours; but from the Negation of our Reſurrection to the Nullity of Chriſt's, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.13.</p>
            <p>This Union is <hi>continued</hi> even while Believers are under the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Grave. The Relation of Chriſt to the Father did not ceaſe when he was detained by Death in the Bowels of the Earth; tho the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97222:19"/>Comforts of that Relation were ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended yet the Relation it ſelf never brake of. So in a State of Death the Union between Chriſt and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers remains: It is the Man who dies, not the Chriſtian. Both parts of the Human Perſon are ſeparated from each other, but neither of them ſeparated from Chriſt: Hence it is that when their Spirits are returned to God, their fleſh doth reſt in Hope, and their Bodies take a joiful and quiet Repoſe in their Beds of Duſt, becauſe He to whom they are ſo dearly and Indiſſolvably United will not leave them under the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Death for ever. But,</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) The Spirit dwells in Believers not only as a <hi>bond of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> between Chriſt and them, but as a <hi>Principle of Power for their Reſurrection.</hi> Rom. 8.11. <hi>But if the Spirit of him that raiſed up Jeſus from the dead, dwell in you; He that raiſed up Chriſt from the Dead, ſhall alſo quicken your Mortal Bodies by his Spirit
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97222:19"/>that dwelleth in you.</hi> The Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Chriſt is aſcribed in the Scripture to all the Perſons in the <hi>Trinity:</hi> It is aſcribed to God the the <hi>Father,</hi> becauſe he is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of action in the Deity as at <hi>Acts</hi> 3.15. and it is aſcribed to him as he is the God of Peace, as inveſted with that Title, becauſe he was the Perſon to whom ſatisfaction was made, as at, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20. And it is aſcribed to the <hi>Son</hi> himſelf becauſe all that he did as Mediator was to be his own <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.19, and <hi>chap.</hi> 10.18. But the efficiency is aſcribed to the <hi>Holy Spirit:</hi> Whether we conſider him as given by the Father, or giving himſelf a Sacrifice for our Sins; he is ſaid, <hi>by the Eternal Spirit</hi> to offer up himſelf <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. ſo whether the act of his Reſurrection be ſpok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en of as done by the Father or by himſelf, yet it is by the <hi>Spirit</hi> which proceeds from both, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. Now the Spirit that dwelleth in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus dwelleth in Believers: And as it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97222:20"/>abode in him, and acted in him to the offering up himſelf to the Death of the Croſs, and afterwards pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſided over his Body in the Grave, and put forth its Power in raiſing him: So far doth it act in Believers while here and preſide over their dead Bodies to the ſame purpoſes. And thus to aſcribe the Reſurrection of Believers to the Spirit of Chriſt is but congruous with other acts of Divine Goodneſs and the precedent workings of the Spirit: For as he quickens the Souls of Believers and raiſes them from Death in Sin, and conforms 'em to the Image of Chriſt, ſo 'tis requiſite that He ſhould be the Author of their Corporeal Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and likeneſs to Chriſt alſo.</p>
            <p>Now the Reſurrection of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers being fixed on theſe Grounds: We ſhall next briefly conſider its <hi>Neceſſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Death,</hi> which was introduc'd by <hi>Sin,</hi> hath been reigning, and acting the part of a Conqueror over Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97222:20"/>and bringing all both juſt and unjuſt under its Dominion; it is neceſſary that ſooner or later it be overcome and ſwallowed up of vict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory; 'tis neceſſary that <hi>ſome</hi> of its Captives be releaſed, that <hi>ſome</hi> Souls be Redeemed from its Power; Otherwiſe,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>The Glory of Chriſt Redeemer would ſuffer a great and perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Eclipſe.</hi> And,</item>
               <item>2. <hi>The Felicity of Believers would never be Compleat and Perfect.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The Glory of Chriſt Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er would ſuffer a great and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Eclipſe. The Perfection of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in their ſeveral Kinds was the Glory of the Creator: To be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from the Power of Sin, and be left under the Power of the Grave, were it ſuppoſeable, would be ſuch an imperfect Redemption as we cannot but apprehend to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97222:21"/>with the Wiſdom, and Power, and Love, and abſolute Perfection of the Redeemer. That Creatures capable of Immortality ſhould be left in a State of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Probation</hi> here, and that their Future State ſhould be according to their preſent Behaviour and Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, carries nothing of inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtency in it: But that theſe Creatures, capable of Immortality, when they have demeaned themſelves aright, and gone through their State of Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al with Approbation, ſhould be left under the Power of Death, and not entred into their Maſters Joy, is ſuch a dealing as we cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive worthy of God: That Death and He who hath the Power of Death, that is, the Devil, ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate their Authority over the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Servants of Chriſt, and take their Reward from them, How <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious</hi> a <hi>Perſon</hi> would this beſpeak our Redeemer to be?</p>
            <p>Moreover as he is the Head of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97222:21"/>Myſtical Body, his Honour ſuffers a viſible Diminution by the Abſence of any Member: There is ſo much loſt of his Praiſes, as ſhould belong to thoſe that are thus kept back: <hi>For who can declare his Righteouſneſs in the Grave? Or Praiſe him in the Houſe of Silence?</hi> Pſalm 88.11, 12. Pſalm 115.17. We are not to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine our Lord ſo careleſs of his own Glory, when he hath already done ſo much for that end, and when it is ſtill in his own Power, (as he is abſolute Lord of the whole unſeen World) to perfect his own Praiſe. As ſurely as he hath triumphed over Death and all Principalities, ſo ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will he make all his Members to Triumph over them, and that for his own Glory: And none ſhall be detained under their Dominion, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſuch as by their own choice while here, remained in an inviolable U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Death and the Prince of Darkneſs, that is, the Devil.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:97222:22"/>
            <p n="2">2. The Felicity of Believers would never be Compleat and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: The Perfection of their <hi>Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> Felicity neceſſarily requires the Concourſe or Union of all that is eſſential to, or conſtitutive of the Perſon: The Body and the Soul from their firſt ſetting out in the World to the Grave run the ſame Race, therefore they muſt enjoy the ſame Reward: There is, 'tis true, a great inequality in their Operations as reſpecting Holineſs, ſo there will be a great inequality in their Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; but both muſt have their proper ſhare: And it would not be beſeeming the Divine Goodneſs, to deal ſo differently, as that the Soul ſhould be Everlaſtingly Happy, and the Body loſt in forgetfulneſs: That the one ſhould be glorified in Heaven, and the other remain in the Duſt. Beſides this, we may juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceive of a fixed innocent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination in the glorified Soul to her former Dear Aſſociate; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97222:22"/>the ſatisfying ſuch an Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by their Re-union, muſt contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the Felicity of the Perſon.</p>
            <p>Their <hi>Relative</hi> of <hi>Mutual</hi> Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs would be likewiſe impaired, if any that truly belonged to their Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber were wanting, and ſtill kept un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Power of Death: For they are all inviolably United in Love, which as it were transforms one into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and cauſes the Glory of every Saint to redound to the Joy of all: And every one both adds to, and ſhares in the Felicity of the whole. Here there are many Vitious Allays of Love among true Chriſtians, and they do not duely ſympathize with one another in their Conditions of Life: But in Heaven they are of one Heart and one Soul; there is an exact A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of Tempers and Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; ſo that could we ſuppoſe the Body of one detained as an Eternal Priſoner of the Grave, and ſuch a ones Happineſs thereby impaired, the whole would ſuffer therein.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:97222:23"/>
            <p>But I come now to the Uſe.</p>
            <p>Now as this Doctrine of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Reſurrection of Believers, being fix'd on the fore-mentioned Grounds and Reaſons, muſt needs be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged a <hi>great Truth;</hi> and one of the true and <hi>faithful Sayings</hi> of God: So upon ſtrict Enquiry, it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear a very <hi>comfortable</hi> Truth: And that</p>
            <p n="1">1. With reſpect to the <hi>preſent Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions</hi> and <hi>Sufferings of this Life;</hi> and particularly the Frailties, and Diſeaſes, and Weakneſs, and Vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of theſe Bodies. The Dictates of Reaſon, and the Preſcriptions of Moraliſts are ineffectual to form the Soul to true Patience and Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, under bodily Sufferings: But Faith and Hope in a bleſſed Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection adminiſters powerful Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port: And as this excels all natural Topicks, ſo all the conſolatory Points in Revealed Religion do ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timately
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97222:23"/>center and terminate in this. <hi>For if our Hope was only in this Life</hi> (whatever may be propounded to us) <hi>we were of all Creatures moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.19. To know that our Bodies ſhall be raiſed to an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, incorruptible Glory; and changed into the likeneſs of Chriſt's Body, makes us more unconcerned about their Condition, and more contented that God ſhould have the entire Diſpoſal of them here: This ſweetens the moſt bitter Cups, alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viates the moſt heavy Burdens, and renders all bodily Diſtempers and Pains ſupportable and eaſie: And furthermore, it directs us ſo to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, ſo to account of, ſo to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove theſe preſent momentary Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, as that <hi>they might Work out for us a far more exceeding and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal weight of Glory,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.17.</p>
            <p n="2">2. With reſpect to our own <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Diſſolution.</hi> This is the thing which Nature ſo much abhors; to come under the Power of Death, to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97222:24"/>be divulſed from all the Enjoyments of Life, to be confined to the dark ſolitude of the Grave, to ſee Man no more in the Land of the Living; this is a frightful and diſquieting Thought: And inaſmuch as this is a thing univerſally known, it is alſo univerſally feared: There is a <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> fear of Death, when this Paſſion is regular both as to its Object and Degree it is excellently Uſeful: As a wiſe Counſellour, or faithful Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian, it keeps Reaſon awake and active, ſo as that it might ſuſtain the Evil in the beſt manner, which it could not prevent. And there is an <hi>inordinate</hi> fear of Death, which as a Tyrannous Maſter doth conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually diſquiet and torment the Soul, and keep a Man all his Life time un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Bondage. The Philoſophers attempted to moderate and govern theſe anxious Fears, but in vain<note n="*" place="margin">Bates <hi>Har. of Attr.</hi> cap. 17.355. p. <hi>Octa.</hi>
               </note>. All that they could op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe againſt this cruel Enemy, while they
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97222:24"/>were without the Knowledge and Belief of a glorious Reſurrection, was ineffectual. But the Goſpel furniſhes us with real Remedies. Chriſtians cannot be afraid to Die when they know they Die in the Lord, and belong to one who will redeem them from the Power of the Grave, and ſwallow up Death in Victory: Were we to be Eternal Captives to Death, and Priſoners of the Grave for ever, there were ſome Reaſon to dread it: But when God ſpeaks to us as to <hi>Jacob</hi> deſcending into <hi>Egypt: Fear not to go down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Grave, I will go down with thee, and I will ſurely bring thee up again:</hi> So that hereby we are as ſure of over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Death as ſuffering it; as ſure of being Conquerors as of being Combatants; how are all <hi>excruciating fears</hi> hereby expelled! In our own Strength indeed, and acting ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately from God we cannot over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: No one can ſave himſelf from going down to the Grave, or by
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97222:25"/>Price or by Force procure his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſement and Diſcharge from its Captivity any more than from its War. But in Relation to God we are more than Conquerors. To be more than Conquerors is to be Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphants: Chriſtians may thus Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in this Perſwaſion, that tho' they taſt Death, the common Lot of every Man, yet they ſhall be redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from it, ſo as not to be hurt by the <hi>ſecond</hi> Death, and neither <hi>Death, nor Life,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall be able to ſeparate them from the Love of God in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Rom. 8.37, 38, 39.</p>
            <p>Neither is this Doctrine of a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Reſurrection, only an <hi>Argument</hi> of <hi>Support</hi> and Comfort under the Apprehenſions of Death; but alſo a Juſt and <hi>Rational Incentive</hi> to <hi>Deſire</hi> our Diſſolution: How willingly did <hi>Elias</hi> let fall his Mantle, that he might aſcend to Heaven? How wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling was <hi>Paul</hi> to be diſſolved, that he might be with Chriſt? How deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly and boldly did the valiant
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97222:25"/>Martyrs encounter with Death, that interpoſed between them and their glorified State? This upbraids our backwardneſs, who profeſs to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened and perſwaded of that bleſſed and perfect World. A <hi>loathneſs</hi> to Die in Chriſtians is direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repugnant to their Hopes, and a reproach to their Chriſtianity it ſelf. We are not to obtain Heaven by an immediate Tranſlation to it; Death is a neceſſary intermediate way, and there is a natural bitterneſs in it, which makes it unpleaſant: 'Tis a dark Paſſage from this to the other World, though under the Cuſtody and Dominion of our gracious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>How's</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. Redeem. over the Inviſ. World, <hi>p. 49.</hi>
               </note>. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this, Believers are ſtill to reckon their Mortality their Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and to bleſs God, that they are not to ſpend their Immortality in the preſent State.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, We ſhould not fear Dying if we did <hi>know</hi> our Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97222:26"/>in Chriſt, if we were <hi>aſſured</hi> that we were of that number, whom he will redeem from the Power of the Grave, and receive to himſelf.</p>
            <p>It muſt be confeſſed, there are but <hi>ſome</hi> whom God will thus Redeem; others are to be left under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of Death, and of him that hath the Power of Death for ever: And theſe have reaſon to fear and Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the thoughts of Death, and much more at its approach; but then conſider, none are among that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber but ſuch as <hi>Voluntarily</hi> put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into it, and wilfully continue, <hi>notwithſtanding</hi> the <hi>means</hi> which the great <hi>Redeemer</hi> uſes to <hi>educe</hi> and <hi>reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> them. Death is no where <hi>perpetual</hi> but where it is <hi>ſelf-procured:</hi> None lie under it, and abide under it, but they that <hi>loved it,</hi> and refuſed to to take hold of the <hi>Paths of Life.</hi> None die unintreſted in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer and his Power, but ſuch as rejected him while they lived. Therefore,</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:97222:26"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Let this <hi>admoniſh</hi> us to take care and provide that we be of that number to whom this bleſſed priviledge belongs: Since it is not common to all but proper only to ſome; with what ſolicitude ſhould we concern our ſelves, and follow on the Enquiry till we arrive at a certainty in this matter? Since the enquiry is of higheſt importance, and admits of a plain and true ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; it can never be juſtified as rational to continue in a dubious uncertainty. Who would not covet to be in a ſpecial Relation to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty and Gracions Redeemer, and to be one of thoſe whom he will Redeem from the Power of the Grave? The knowledge of this alone can preſerve the true comfort of our lives; and fill us in Death with Joy <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſpeakable</hi> and <hi>full of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> Let us therefore with aſſiduous di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence endeavour to make our <hi>Call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Election</hi> (and therewith our <hi>Glorious Reſurrection</hi>) <hi>ſure.</hi> This
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97222:27"/>matter will quickly be brought to an Iſſue with every one of us; <hi>either</hi> Death will Triumph over us, and prey upon us as Eternal Trophies of its Conqueſt; or through Divine Grace and Love we ſhall be delivered and Triumph over it.</p>
            <p>There are <hi>Two</hi> or <hi>Three</hi> Things, will <hi>aſcertain</hi> our State, and let us into the Knowledge of what our <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Iſſue</hi> will be.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Are we <hi>Regenerate Creatures:</hi> We are naturally Apoſtates from God, and in open defiance againſt his Soveraignty and Laws; and there can be nothing but a fearful Expectation or looking for of Death and Vengeance which ſhall devour and conſume ſuch Adverſaries; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til we ceaſe to be Adverſaries, until the contrariety of our Natures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him be ſubdued, and we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come new Creatures. Our Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions cannot rationally be altered, but upon a precedent Change of State. The Reſurrection of Chriſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97222:27"/>is the Ground of this bleſſed Hope in Believers (as hath been ſhewn) but their Regeneration is the <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> of it. A Soul that paſſes out of this World unrenewed, muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver expect a Reunion with a raiſed <hi>Glorified</hi> Body. The Body indeed ſhall be raiſed and reunited to the Soul, but it will be in order to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat the Miſery of the Sinner. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption from the Power of Sin, and Redemption from the Power of Death are <hi>Coextenſive,</hi> and have both the ſame Subjects, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6. <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and Holy is he who hath part in the firſt Reſurrection, on ſuch the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Death hath no Power.</hi> There is the <hi>Priviledge,</hi> and there is the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> of the Perſon to whom it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs: It is in vain to think of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving the Divine Order, or ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting what God hath joined toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: None ever was or ſhall be ſo bleſſed as to be exempt from the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the ſecond Death, but ſuch as are Holy, and have Part in the firſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97222:28"/>Reſurrection. Though the Soul be the immediate Subject of Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet it reſpects the whole Perſon: The Underſtanding, and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and Will, and Affections are all changed in this Work: And the bodily Members and Senſes are deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated by the renewed Soul, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in new Services; and are no more the Members of Unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but Inſtruments of Service to Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.19. The Laws of the great Redeemer are the Rule of Duty to the entire Man, and are obeyed or violated by the Soul and Body in Conjunction. Now where there hath been this entire Obedience yielded by a Man renewed in his whole Conſtitution, it ſhall receive a juſt recompence of Reward; and thoſe that have followed Chriſt in <hi>the Regeneration; when the Son of Man ſhall ſit on the Throne of his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, they ſhall ſit with him judging the Twelve Tribes of Iſrael?</hi> Mat. 19.28.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Are we <hi>Dead with Chriſt: If we
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97222:28"/>be Dead with Chriſt, we believe that we ſhall alſo live with him. If we be planted together with him in the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Death, we ſhall be alſo in the likeneſs of his Reſurrection: If we ſuffer with him we ſhall reign with him,</hi> Rom. 6.5, 8. Our likeneſs to Chriſt muſt be begun in our preſent embo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died State. This is the fixed Order of Heaven. The other World is the World of Perfection, where the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Chriſt or of the Devil is compleated, according to which of them was begun here upon Earth.</p>
            <p>None can have Communion with the Redeemer in his glorious Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, but ſuch as have Fellowſhip with him in his Sufferings, and are conformable to his Death: <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10. A Man that continues to Live, cannot while ſuch, be the ſubject of Reſurrection, He muſt firſt Die. So our Self-denial and Mortification, and Dying with Chriſt as neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly precedes our Communion with him in his glorious Reſurrection.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:97222:29"/>
            <p n="3">3. Are our <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> now <hi>with God and Chriſt in Heaven.</hi> Nothing leſs than an <hi>Heavenly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation</hi> can juſtifie our looking for a <hi>Saviour, who ſhall change our vile Bodies</hi> into the <hi>Image of his moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Body,</hi> Phil. 3.20, 21. A Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Temper of Mind, and an Heart unlimitedly engaged in the World, doth abſolutely contradict the Hopes of a bleſſed Reſurrection, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception into Heaven. It is the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Hope (as it is a Chriſtian Grace) to engage the Soul in a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Purſuit of that which is hoped for: And alſo to give it a deep Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of its Object before it is actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enjoyed: Therefore if we don't ſavour heavenly Things above all carnal and worldly Delights, and ſeek them with the greateſt Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, our Hopes are <hi>Fallacious:</hi> The Wiſe and Holy God cannot act ſo <hi>Inconſiſtently</hi> with Himſelf. (How Inconſiſtent ſoever Mens Actions and Hopes may be) as to beſtow Heaven
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97222:29"/>and Glory upon one that never deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or eſteemed or ſought it, that would always prefer the Honours and Emoluments of the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it. This would be to violate the Rules of <hi>Diſcrimination,</hi> which he himſelf hath fixed; and ſuch an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious Amplification</hi> of that bleſſed Kingdom as would leave it almoſt undeſirable; and the Priviledges of Chriſtians would ceaſe to be Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges when others may have an equal ſhare in them.</p>
            <p>Theſe Enquiries do in ſhort recur to this. Have we a ſure Intereſt in Chriſt who is the Prince and Lord of Life? Have we received him in all theſe Reſpects wherein he is to be received, and abſolutely reſigned our ſelves to him as our Lord and Saviour? Hath there paſſed ſuch mutual Acts between us and him of giving and receiving, as that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon He may be truly called ours,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97222:30"/>and we as truly ſaid to be his? He will finally redeem none but his own. Have we remaining Indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this in our Hearts and Lives? Have our Courſe in this World been ordered agreeably thereto in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Dependance and Subjection? In a <hi>Word,</hi> Is our cloſure with him ſincere and truly Unitive, and do we accordingly live to him, and with him, and carefully abide in him while we are in this Earthly Tabernacle? If ſo, we may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend our departing Spirits into his Hands, and our Fleſh may reſt in Hope, and we ſhall have Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and not be aſhamed at his Coming. The infallible Word hath given us this, as the only Ground of our Hope, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.12. <hi>He that hath the Son hath Life: And He that hath not the Son hath not Life.</hi> John 11.25, 26. <hi>I am the Reſurrection and the Life, He that believeth in me, though he were Dead, yet ſhall he
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97222:30"/>live, and whoſoever liveth and belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in me ſhall never Die.</hi> Every true Believer hath a Life in him (by Vertue of his Union with Chriſt) which is Immortal, and not liable to the touch of Death, a Life that ſhall not End in the rottenneſs and darkneſs of the Grave, or in a Horrid Hell, but run on through the Territories of Death and the Grave into Everlaſting Life. And beſides this, His bodily Life in the Reunion of Soul and Body ſhall be revived; the <hi>Pains,</hi> or (as ſome rather read it) the <hi>Bands</hi> of Death ſhall be looſed, and it ſhall be impoſſible for him, any more then the Prince of Life himſelf to whom he is United, to be holden by it, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.24.</p>
            <p>Now having made this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of the Doctrine in <hi>General;</hi> I ſhall make ſome further Improvement of it, as it refers <hi>Particularly</hi> to the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97222:31"/>Caſe at Preſent before our View. That which is ſpoken of Believers indefinitely, that they ſhall not be left under the Power of Death and the Grave, but be raiſed and glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, may I doubt not without one diſagreeing Judgment or Voice be truly ſpoken of the Perſon whoſe Deceaſe hath given this ſpecial occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and additional to the uſual Buſineſs of this Day. Therefore, Let this Point aſſiſted by this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Inſtance, work ſome correſpondent Effects, and leave ſome ſuitable Impreſſions upon us: And what can thoſe be but of <hi>Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> and <hi>Peaceful Submiſſion or Satisfaction</hi> of Mind?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let this Doctrine aſſiſted by this known Inſtance, impreſs us to Endeavours of Imitation. When a Man Proſpers in the World and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes in the Favour of his Fellow-Creatures, we preſently enquire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97222:31"/>the Methods and Rules of ſuch a ones Conduct, and are ready to govern our Selves, as near as our Circumſtances will admit, by the ſame. How much more ſtudiouſly ſhould we imitate one, that in the the trueſt Senſe is Proſperous and Happy, and being entituled to the Divine Favour both in Life and Death, is therefore Intereſted in his full and final Redemption? Tho <hi>ſuch</hi> an <hi>one</hi> is now gone from our lower World, and hath left us, yet <hi>Her Example</hi> remains. We have known <hi>what manner of entring in She had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 1.9. 2 Tim. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>and Her man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Life, Purpoſe, Faith, Long-Suffering, Charity and Patience:</hi> Her Temper was Rare and Excellent, and truly deſerving of Emulation: Her natural Patience and Fortitude of Mind, Great and Uncommon. Her Prudence and Diſcretion obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as well as uſeful in the Sphere
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97222:32"/>wherein She acted. Her Contempt of the Vanity and deluding Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the World; Her Holy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference of Life, and Reſignation to the Will of God, are more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to be imitated becauſe they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend more upon our own Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours than the former. The natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral chearfulneſs and pleaſantneſs of Her Spirit was Great and Delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, yet Grave and Solid: But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering She was not only under, but had received the Sentence of Death in Her Self, it muſt be aſcribed in great Part to <hi>Supernatural</hi> Reaſons, and a Pre-aſſurance of Future Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs. This is evident by the Fears She often expreſſed, leaſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers knowing Her outward and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, better than Her inward State, might make cenſorious and prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Conſtructions, and believe Her rather inſenſible of, than Reſigned to the Divine Will.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:97222:32"/>
            <p>Her Death was no leſs <hi>Serene</hi> and <hi>Calm</hi> than Her Life: With Her won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Compoſure of Mind She bore Her laſt bodily Diſorder, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Sigh</hi> or <hi>Motion</hi> expired in a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; as if it had been deſigned She ſhould Experience a Victory o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Death, almoſt without conflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with it, or taſting its bitterneſs. With that tenderneſs did Her Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Redeemer Govern and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule the Stroak of Death, having before diſarmed it of its Sting! So gently were the Bands of Life un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twiſted!</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſighing Part</hi> She hath left to us, who are yet in the Vale of Tears, and have the Valley of the Shadow of Death yet before us to paſs through: And how can a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints do leſs than Sigh, when there is one Hand and Heart the leſs to be lifted up in its Prayers,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97222:33"/>and one Inſtrument, or well tuned String the leſs in its Conſort of Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes? How can a Family do leſs than Sigh, when deprived of ſo amiable and uſeful a Relative? Such Stroaks cannot but be lamented: But let our principal Care be, that the Perſon hereby removed be <hi>Imitated;</hi> in Her Humble and Truly Charitable Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and in Her Holy Inoffenſive Life and Deportment; whereby She adorned the Doctrine of Chriſt, and recommended Religion as an amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and acceptable Inſtitution to all that Converſed with Her: <hi>Let us be followers of Her in all Things, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in She was a Follower of Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.1. <hi>And ſhew the ſame Diligence to the full Aſſurance of Hope to the End, and be Followers of Her, who through Faith and Patience do now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Promiſes,</hi> Heb. 6.11, 12.</p>
            <p>And it is reaſonable that all <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,</hi> according to the Degree of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97222:33"/>their Relation ſhould account them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves more obliged to this Uſe. May Her Example therefore with Her Name live in their Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance: Particularly may <hi>Children remember, and not forſake the Law of their Mother,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 1.8. Prov. 20.3.</note> but ſo attend to it as that <hi>they may be bleſſed after Her.</hi> May Servants alſo, <hi>Remember Her that had the Rule over them, and ſpoke to them</hi> (by an Exemplary Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) <hi>the Word of God, whoſe Faith follow, conſidering the End of Her Converſation,</hi> Heb. 13.7. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding Part of a Chriſtians Life does not only bear a Teſtimony to His or Her preceding Courſe, but demonſtrate the ſingular Advantage of Faith and Holineſs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (being obſerved) is mightily Aſſiſtant to our Imitation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let this Doctrine attended with this Inſtance, impreſs us, to a <hi>Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97222:34"/>Submiſſion</hi> of Mind, and <hi>Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> in the Divine Pleaſure: It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Chriſtians to attain a ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive and ſatisfied Temper through the Power of their Faith and Hope: How abſur'd is it for ſuch to expect and find more Cure of their Grief and Sorrow from Time, than from Reaſon and Grace? Though there be a ſmartneſs in the Diſpenſation, yet receive it with ſubmiſſive Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; conſidering, it is <hi>God who hath done it:</hi> Pſalm 39.9. This ſad Event is not the Fruit of Blind Chance, but both as to Time and Manner, the Act of Infinite <hi>Wiſdom</hi> that cannot err, and of Infinite <hi>Power</hi> that cannot be reſiſted, and (which is more <hi>Conſolatory</hi>) of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite <hi>Goodneſs</hi> and <hi>Kindneſs</hi> to his <hi>Departed Servant.</hi> Can we imagine, that a glorified Soul does wiſh to be again embodied for a Reſidence in this our lower World? Or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a painful, afflicted, and tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:97222:34"/>Life before the Bleſſedneſs of Her Coeleſtial State, and the hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Reſt of Her Dear Aſſociate? Can we imagine that a Glorified Soul is in the leaſt diſſatisfied with Her Tranſlation, or leaving the Body; when the Body (as She knows) is not left in Hell nor ſuffer'd to ſee Corruption?</p>
            <p>Was not this <hi>Her</hi> Habitual Senſe while remaining among us, that to Depart and be with Chriſt was beſt? And was not this the Ultimate and Higheſt End of our Solemn and Renewed Addreſſes to God in <hi>Days</hi> of Prayer on Her Behalf; while we profeſſed to ask Her Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in the Fleſh, with a ſincere and moſt abſolute Reſignation to the Divine Will? If then not only the <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>God</hi> be done, but <hi>Her Will</hi> accompliſhed, and alſo our Prayers anſwered, it is reaſonable that <hi>Our Wills</hi> ſhould be abundantly
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97222:35"/>ſatisfied: And it cannot be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than unreaſonable, that Our Wills ſhould be repugnant either to God's or Her's, which with a moſt joyful Concurrence have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Place, and are now to remain the ſame for ever. To be thus Self-willed in ſuch a Caſe, as it carries much of Unreaſonableneſs and Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religion in it, ſo likewiſe an Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency with a pure Rational and Chriſtian Love towards our depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Relatives. Our Saviour tells his Diſciples whoſe loſs of him, and of his Bodily Preſence was much greater than any of ours) <hi>If ye loved me, ye would rejoice becauſe I ſaid I go to my Father,</hi> John 14.28. A true and pure Affection does directly and chiefly Terminate in the Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and Exaltation of the Perſon loved. Now Death is a ſure Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to Believers; and their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent into the Grave is an infallible ſtep to their Glorious Preferment.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:97222:35"/>
            <p>To look upon the Caſe before us with an Eye of Senſe, it is all over black and ſad: Death hath killed and taken Poſſeſſion of one of us; it hath turned a living Creature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a dead Clod, it is laid among ſuch, and Buried in the Grave, and our Eye of Senſe carries us no further. But when by an infallible Word, we are aſſured that the Power of Death ſhall be aboliſhed, and this Mortality put on Immortality, and this Corruption put on Incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we muſt no more Mourn as thoſe that are without Hope. To Conſider and Believe, that <hi>God will redeem his own from the Power of the Grave, and receive them;</hi> takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all Cauſes of an unremitting and reliefleſs Sorrow, at his taking away any of ours, of whom we are perſwaded that they belonged to him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
